Finding aid to the Smith College Special Collections records CA.MS.00408
Smith College Archives
Smith College Special Collections records
approximately 1873-2018
Smith College Archives
CA.MS.00408
13.958 linear feet (38 containers)
33 Gigabytes (2,350 digital files)
The Smith College Archives document the life of the College by collecting materials created by students, faculty, administrative and departmental staff during the course of their time here. The Sophia Smith Collection at Smith College is an internationally recognized repository of manuscripts, archives, photographs, periodicals and other primary sources in women's history. This collection contains the administrative records of the College Archives and Sophia Smith Collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These materials were transferred to College Archives on an ongoing basis, including larger accessions in 1991, 1998, 2002 and 2015.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use with following restrictions on access:
All office files are closed for 10 years following their date of creation.
Biographical / Historical
The Smith College Archives document the life of the College by collecting materials created by students, faculty, administrative and departmental staff during the course of their time here.
The Sophia Smith Collection at Smith College is an internationally recognized repository of manuscripts, archives, photographs, periodicals and other primary sources in women's history. It was founded in 1942 to be the library's distinctive contribution to the college's mission of educating women.
Since 2014, the College Archives, Sophia Smith Collection, and Mortimer Rare Book Collection have been adminstratively unified as the Smith College Special Collections.
Scope and Contents
Smith College Special Collections records include directors' chronological files and correspondence; articles about Special Collections; meeting notes; Special Collections position searches; donor files; deeds of gift; accession records; the SSC 50th Anniversary celebration files; exhibit materials; materials related to production of "Creating Women's History: The Sophia Smith Collection" video; and digital images and av recordings of special collection events.
Other Finding Aids
This online finding aid currently provides detailed description of only the most recent addition to this collection. Additional materials are described in unpublished lists that can be sent to you upon request by contacting specialcollections@smith.edu
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
This collection contains materials received in digital form that are not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content.
Libraries; Libraries--Special collections--Women--History--Sources; Archives; Women's history archives; Exhibitions--United States.; Deeds; Electronic records; Sophia Smith Collection; Smith College Archives
- College Archives and SSC (Box 30)
- College Archives and SSC (Box 30.1)
- College Archives and SSC (Box 31)
- Exhibit Labels A-F (Box 32)
- Exhibit Labels G-E, 1879-1909 (Box 32.1)
- Exhibits, 1879-1901 (Box 33)
- Exhibit Labels, 1910-1930 (Box 34)
- Exhibit Labels, 1910-1950 (Box 35)
- Exhibit Labels, 1951-1970 (Box 36)
- College Archives Exhibit Labels A-M, 1984-1993 (Box 36.1)
- College Archives Exhibit Labels N-Z, 1984-1993 (Box 36.2)
- College Archives Exhibit Labels A-H, 1994-2010 (Box 36.3)
- College Archives Exhibits I-Sp, 1994-2010 (Box 36.4)
- College Archives Exhibits St-Z, 1994-2010 (Box 36.4.1)
- College Archives, exhibit files - Women of Color (Box 36.4.2)
- Exhibit - "Power of Women's Voices" - Sophia Smith Collection, 2007 (Box 36.4.3)
- Sophia Smith Collection Exhibit Labels A-Ce, 1974-2010 (Box 36.5)
- Sophia Smith Collection Reading Room Exhibits C-L, 1974-2010 (Box 36.6)
- Sophia Smith Collection Exhibit Labels Ma-No, 1974-2010 (Box 36.6.1)
- Sophia Smith Collection Reading Room exhibits No (2) - Z (Box 36.6.2)
- Recent gifts and purchases of the year, 1995-1996 (Box 36.7)
- Sophia Smith Collection exhibit labels - Mair Room/Collacott Room, 1986-2010 (Box 36.8)
- Grierson, Margaret logs (carbons A-Z), 1964-1965 (Box 37)
- Monthly Gift Lists, September 1954 -June 1965 (Box 37.1)
- Booksellers - M. Grierson (Box 37.2)
- Daybooks - M. Grierson, Sept. 15 1950 - Aug. 23 1954 (Box 37.3)
- Daybooks - M. Grierson, Aug. 24, 954 - March 31, 1958 (Box 37.4)
- Daybooks - M. Grierson, April 1, 1958 - March 6, 1962 (Box 37.5)
- Daybooks - M. Grierson, March 7, 1962 - May 31, 1965 (Box 37.6)
- Mary-Elizabeth Murdock committee files (Box 37.7)
- Certificates of Gift (Box 37.8)
- Certificate of Gift (Box 37.8a)
- Accessions record book (Box 37.9)
- College Archives records transfer authorization forms (Box 37.10)
- Non-donors correspondence (Box 37.11)
- Accession routing slips, 1984/85 - 1988/89 (Box 37.12)
- Accession routing slips, 1989-1990 (Box 37.13)
- Accession records, 1990/91-1993/94 (Box 37.14)
- Creating Women's History: The Sophia Smith Collection video, 2001; 2018-A-0018; Amy Hague; Follet, Joyce; Rockefeller, Terry; 1 items (1 video on DVD); .50 Gigabytes (1 digital file)
  Scope and Contents
  Documentary on the Sophia Smith Collection, women's history archive at Smith College. Produced, written and directed by Joyce Follet and Terry Kay Rockefeller, 2001. This brief film highlights Smith College's pioneering contributions to the movement that is revolutionizing the writing and teaching of history. It chronicles the 1942 founding of the nation's oldest women's manuscripts collection by historian Mary Ritter Beard and archivist Margaret Storrs Grierson and features cameo appearances by:
  Gloria Steinem Rebecca Walker, Third Wave feminist Amy Richards, Third Wave feminist Jan Peterson, Grassroots activist Frances Fox Piven, Political scientist/Activist Daniel Horowitz, Historian Linda Gordon, Historian Linda Kerber, Historian
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  This DVD was donated to the College Archives by Amy Hague, May 24, 2018.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Use of the original media (DVD) is restricted for preservation reasons. A digital file copy is available for research use.
  Related Materials
  2 VHS copies of this video are in the College Archives, in RG 100 (AV): V214, V215. The original production materials, including raw footage were transferred to the College Archives from the Sophia Smith Collection in 2010 (accession 2010-A-00038).
  Existence and Location of Copies
  Additional copies of this video are located in the College Archives Audiovisual collection (100 AV), in VHS format.
  Amy Hague
- Special Collections events: photos and audiovisual recordings, 2003-2015; Accession 2018-A-0097; Sophia Smith Collection; 32 Gigabytes (2,350 digital files)
  Audiovisual recordings and still photos of events sponsored by Smith College Special Collections. Also included are photographs of Special Collections classes, staff gatherings and individual staff, archival activities, and building spaces.
  Some of the events represented include:
  "Righting the Wrongs of Rock History: Women, Gender and Rock": a panel discussion introducing the Women of Rock Oral History Project, October, 22, 2015
  "An Activist Archives": Marielena Hincapié of the National Immigration Law Center and Miriam Yeung of the National Asian Pacific American Women's Forum in conversation with Sophia Smith Collection Activist in Residence, Sara Gould, April 2014.
  "Loretta Ross: Basic Skills of Organizing for Social Justice Workshops", February 2013
  "An Activist Archives: The Sophia Smith Collection at 70": featuring Alison Bechdel, Marianne Bullock, Katsi Cook, Anna Holley, Loretta Ross, and Gloria Steinem, February 2013
  "The Power of Women's Voices Conference: Celebrating 65 Years of Collecting Women's History at Smith College", featuring Margie Adam, Loretta Ross, Gloria Steinem, and many others, 2007
  Gloria Steinem speaking on "The Future of Feminism," 2007
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  This content was received in digital form and most of it is not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access.
  A number of these recorded events are available for viewing on the Libraries' website.
  Other Finding Aids
  See the linked file list for more information.
  Libraries--Special collections--Women--History--Sources; Smith College--History--Sources; Smith College--Students.; Sophia Smith Collection; Smith College Archives